Now let's get started. Uh and today we
will be finishing up model based
reinforcement learning specifically a
way to use a learn model with synthetic
data generation. uh and when to use
model based reinforcement learning. And
then we're going to be talking about
multitask imitation learning and
reinforcement learning uh including ways
to conditions on tasks uh different
tasks as goal reaching tasks and uh an
approach called hindsight reabeling
which you'll be reimplementing.
Cool. Um so let's get back to model
based reinforcement learning. So last
time we talked about a scenario where we
learn some model. Uh that model could be
a deterministic model. It could also be
um modeling a distribution over uh over
next states. And uh in particular uh you
could think about it as trying to
approximate the distribution over uh the
next state given the current state in
action. And you can use this model to
actually um kind of predict what will
happen in the future. And for example,
if you have a uh an action that you
think you might take or multiple actions
you think you might take, you can use uh
this estimated distribution to generate
or imagine what might happen in the
future if you were to take those
actions.
Uh we talked about an approach to
behavior that's quite different from
learning a policy where we're not
actually explicitly ma learning a
mapping from states to actions and
instead on the fly we are thinking
through for a given state what actions
we should take. We called this planning
and we talked about how this sort of
planning can be done with gradient-based
or sampling based optimization over your
next future horizon. Uh then we also
talked about how it's important to
update the model using the data
collected uh because then you'll be able
to actually learn a better model in the
realms that you want to use that model.
Uh and then periodically we also talked
about how you can replan to help account
for mistakes, account for errors in the
model um and uh and also react to
changes in the environment.
Cool. Um the pros of this sort of
planning approach is that it's simple.
It's easy to plug in different goals or
rewards if you have um a general enough
model possibly even at test time. Uh and
the downside is that it's compute
intensive at test time. It requires a
lot of test time compute at inference
time. Uh and this particular
instantiation was only practical for
short horizon problems uh where um or or
for very shaped wards where you can plan
over some shorter horizon uh rather than
considering like an extremely long
horizon.
Um
and the reason why short horizons
there's kind of two reasons why this is
only applicable to short horizons. One
is that as you increase the horizon uh
it get becomes even more compute
intensive and the second reason is that
the model is not very accurate um when
you try to uh apply it multiple times to
generate a long trajectory.
Cool. Um now there's a second way that
you can use these kinds of learn models.
Uh and that is to learn a policy. Uh and
so that's what we'll talk about right
now. Uh and the key idea is that we
could actually use this model of the
future uh this kind of learned simulator
to augment any sort of data that we've
collected.
So say that uh in the real world or the
real environment we've collected some
data. Uh so we have uh some
trajectories. Some of this data could
also have been provided to us in an
offline data set. Uh and so maybe our
the data that we have in the real
environment looks something like this.
Um does anyone have thoughts on how we
might use our um like ways in which we
might want to use our learned model to
augment this data set right here?
like how would we go like procedurally
like what would we do to try to generate
synthetic data? Yeah. So the thought
there was that you could take um you
said you could take like the last state
uh and then generate more from there. So
you could add on to uh your the like the
last state here. So that's one thing you
could do. Um other thoughts on things
you could do? Yeah. So something like
Dagger where you take the first part um
that's run by the policy and then the
second part that's kind of from the
model. So it's kind of similar to this
maybe but maybe you do it earlier. Is
that what you're saying? Yeah. So um you
don't just have to start at the end. You
could also start anywhere in the middle
as well. So you could for example uh
generate kind of trajectories from
really any sort of state in your buffer
in your data set. Uh and then if you
were to do something like that, then you
would uh kind of be able to generate um
data that looks like this where
everything that is in red is kind of uh
synthetic data uh or data that was
imagined using your model uh and then
everything in black is the real data
from the environment.
Now, um, one thing that we talked about
before is that our model is not, uh, is
not very good to be like you can't
really trust it if you're to make a
really long roll out. And so, one thing
that you can do is keep these
trajectories very short. Uh, and so you
could actually like instead of having
these be almost as long as your original
directories, uh, you could actually
change them to be just little short uh,
rollouts that look uh, something like
this. And that basically add a little
bit more coverage around the trajectory
in your data. Uh, and so that would look
kind of something like this.
And that's often the kind of something
like this picture is often uh more like
what people uh find works really well in
practice um because the um because of
inaccuracies in your model.
And so kind of specifically uh say we
have some example real trajectory
then
maybe the first way that you could think
about creating data uh maybe was wasn't
the first way that you guys thought
about it but one simple thing you could
do is just start from initial states and
generate full trajectories as if it were
the real environment. Um but the
downside there is that the model may not
be accurate for long horizons. And so
you won't be able to actually get very
good state coverage if you only start at
the initial state distribution and don't
actually um and [clears throat]
uh uh because you only want to use
fairly short rollouts. Um you can also
generate partial trajectories from the
initial states. Uh but this won't give
you good coverage of later states. And
so um what um kind of one thing that
kind of gets the the best of both
worlds, it gets you good coverage and
also um allows you to use short
trajectories to generate these kind of
sort of partial trajectories uh from all
of the states in your real data set.
So then what the full algorithm looks
like is you will first
collect real data.
Uh we can call this uh dn like before.
And then we will want to like update our
model
using the real data so that our model is
um as accurate as it can be.
And then we can sample we can generate
data. And the way this generation
process will look like
is first sample
some s from your
your real data and then
generate a short trajectory starting
from S where you will
roll out your policy or whatever
exploration policy you have
starting from S
but then um we'll be doing this roll out
inside your learned model.
Uh and so this will be inside uh kind of
the world uh that kind of is um
instantiated from your learn model and
not in the real environment. This data
will go into um some
other data set. Uh maybe we can call it
D genen uh for D generated data
and then at the end you can simply
update your policy using both the real
data and the generated data. So
update pi theta
using DN and
D generated
and then repeat this process.
Whoops, I misspelled real.
Uh, so the question is, if you're only
generating short trajectories, does that
take longer to converge to some goal? So
the
um
you can think of it as kind of
supplementing the data that you have so
far. And the things that are like the
things in your uh when you start from
states that are closer to the goal uh
from [snorts]
uh when you generate data there then
you'll uh be close to getting rewards
and you'll be able to update. um the
when you're further uh this doesn't mean
that like you this data won't
necessarily reach the goal but you'll um
with reinforcement learning algorithms
you'll be able to um understand uh like
some of this data might feed back onto
like feed into states that are in the
data. Uh and when you use reinforcement
learning, you can then learn that um
like as an example, maybe you have a
real trajectory that kind of takes a
path that is maybe not the most direct
path and then you start learning a
policy that knows like maybe I should
kind of shortcut this. Then your model
uh when you explore that in your
synthetic data, you might actually um
this might actually help you learn like
a better policy by using this kind of
data. Um in terms of convergence speed
or kind of uh speed in which you'll get
a good policy. Uh the generally this
will allow you to
it might require um generally the the
thing that we're often trying to
minimize is the amount of real data that
we need right here. And this will allow
you to get a good policy with less real
data uh by using these red trajectories.
Yeah. So the question is how do we get
rewards in this case? So the um I didn't
I haven't explicitly written out here
because sometimes you um sometimes you
might know the form of the reward
function. Uh but if it um or you might
have learned a reward function in which
case uh in the like original RL problem
in which case you can use that. Uh if
you don't um
if you uh you didn't learn a reward
function um and the real world just
gives you the rewards as part of this
data then when you train this model
you'll have you'll need it for it to um
either this model or a separate model to
also learn a reward function with
supervised learning. Um so the question
was about compute. So the this is going
to be more compute intensive during
training uh than if you were to not use
this uh especially because sometimes the
models that you might be learning uh in
some cases they're the models that
you're learning usually rolling out
through them is takes compute. Uh you're
kind of trading data in the environment
for compute. Uh and one of the reasons
why that trade-off is often favorable is
because collecting online data in the
real environment might be unsafe. uh or
it might just be really expensive if you
have to run experiments on like physical
equipment. Um the unlike planning
however this is not more compute
intensive at test time uh because you're
using the synthetic data to update a
policy and then at test time you're
running that policy as your final
behavior.
Cool.
So the algorithm on the slides, we
collect data, we update our model. This
model may also model rewards uh by
trying to mimic the data from the
environment. Then we will collect these
short rollouts uh by kind of using our
model um starting from states in the
real data and then we'll update the
policy uh and optionally also update uh
any sort of value function using the
aggregated aggregated data.
Um one other thing to note
uh about this is that it is compatible
with a variety of reinforcement learning
algorithms. So step four you can use a
variety of algorithms. Um here uh you
can even use onpolicy reinforcement
learning algorithms as well. uh in
particular if you have an on policy
algorithm that needs data from uh the
exact PI theta that you're taking a
gradient step on all that means that PI
theta has to be the policy that was
collecting the synthetic data through
the model.
Um, cool. And so, and yeah, so with
regard to this last update, um, here
we're using both the data from the
environment and the data from the model.
Uh, there are actually also some policy
updates that only use data from the
model uh, and find that that works uh,
fine as well. Uh, the so you can choose
to use either both or or just use the
data uh, from the model. Yeah. So this
make um this only makes sense when you
have an estimate of the reward function
and if you don't then you won't be able
to update your policy on the generated
data. So the question is the learning
stable when you use the synthetic data.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um, so you may be in a
scenario where you're adding a lot of
synthetic data and so like how much
synthetic data you generate and how you
balance that data uh in this last update
is like um kind of might depend on like
how good you think your model is. Uh in
terms of stability uh the I think that
like one we'll talk about pros and cons
on the next slide. Uh and but one
downside of the these kinds of
algorithms is they do introduce
additional hyperparameters. because you
have to train this model and if for
example your model training like for
whatever reason it it didn't uh do well
then you might end up in a scenario
where uh the algorithm like performs
more poorly because those
hyperparameters weren't well tuned and
so you can see issues there. Um but
otherwise uh the
um
this sort of like uh if you have a a
fairly accurate model uh you don't
usually don't have issues otherwise with
stability.
Um so let's talk a little bit about when
to use this sort of synthetic data and
and when to use modelbased reinforcement
learning. So generally uh the way to
think about it is that there's
potentially really big upsides with
model based reinforcement learning and
also potentially big downsides. Uh the
big upside is that uh if you can learn a
pretty good model then it is immensely
useful uh to be able to predict the
future uh and you can get away with
using far far less real data uh by using
the data that's generated. uh and so in
domains where it's feasible to learn a
model uh it's really really useful uh
you could also do the kind of test time
planning as well um and generally I
guess maybe one other point that's not
on the slides with regard to upsides is
that it it seems like this notion of
being able to anticipate uh kind of
future states as an outcome of your
actions that seems like a fairly
fundamental thing that our models uh
should at least have some understanding
for.
Uh, one other thing that we actually
didn't talk about is there are also
scenarios where the model can be trained
without reward labels. And for example,
if you have if some of your data if some
of your real data has rewards and some
of it doesn't have rewards, the part
that doesn't have rewards, you can train
your model on uh and your model can
actually leverage potentially more data
than what a model free reinforcement
learning method can use. Um, and so
that's quite nice. uh and there are
scenarios where you might be able to
collect very large amounts of data
without rewards and a small amount of
data with rewards.
Um and then the other thing is that the
model is somewhat t task agnostic and so
if it was trained on a broad enough data
distribution sometimes you can transfer
this model across different tasks or
across different rewards. And um and so
for example, if you're not if your goal
isn't just to learn one task, but to
learn many different tasks, uh this sort
of transferability uh is useful.
Um so those are the big upsides. What
about the big downsides?
Uh one downside is that the model
doesn't optimize for task performance
and errors. um because it's trying to
like uh for example if you have image
observations or or your states are
images then it's trying to get the
details in the pixels to line up uh and
that for example the the color of the
sky is like the correct color for
example and that in some ways often
times is uh not actually what you care
about in terms of learning a good
policy. Uh so there's this mismatch
between what you're optimizing for when
you train a model and what you actually
might care about in terms of downstream
policy performance.
Um, sometimes it's really hard to learn
a good model. Sometimes it's harder to
learn a good model than it is to learn a
good policy. Uh, in these cases, uh,
usually you don't want to learn models
because the, um, you're kind of then
presenting a harder problem, um, than
the actual downstream problem you might
care about.
Um, and then the last thing that I
alluded to before is that it's another
thing you have to train. And so there's
more hyperparameters and it's also more
compute intensive. uh and so be because
of these like big upsides and big
downsides generally whether to use
whether to try to learn this kind of
predictive model depends a lot on the
domain and how hard it is to learn that
kind of model. Yeah. So the question is
um what are a few examples of the
additional hyperparameters? Um the main
thing is all comes down to like this
step two right here um which is that you
need to design the architecture of the
model of this predictive model. uh and
it might need to be a completely
different architecture from the policy
if you're going to be generating images
or states. Uh the second is that uh you
need a learning rate. You need to know
how long to train that for like how many
epochs um any regularization for that
model. Uh basically everything that
might go into training um a model like
this. One more thing on that previous
question. Um beyond training this model
there's also hyperparameters with regard
to the length of these rollouts um and
how much uh synthetic data to generate.
Uh so the question is do we keep on
collecting um data after each policy
update. So uh this is as written this is
like an online algorithm. Uh you can
actually also develop completely offline
versions model based RL versions as well
where you have a fixed prior data set
and you augment that data set with a
model and then you train a policy and
you're done. Um this uh in this case we
have an online algorithm where we then
continue to kind of collect real data
update our model uh and and so forth.
The um
this can be done in an off policy way or
an on policy way. So that's going to
come down to when you do this update, is
it going to only use the DN and the DGEN
from this iteration or also from
previous iterations. Uh and the that's
going to depend on what algorithm you
use to update your policy. So generally
models are very flexible. You can use
them um offline, on policy, off policy
and so forth. Yeah. So the question is
um how hard is a model to like how hard
is it to learn a model compared to a
policy? uh it's extremely domain
dependent. So the um say for example you
are say you're in like a maze. Uh so
you're trying to learn like how to get
from here to here. Maybe there's like
some walls uh and you need to uh kind of
figure out how to kind of get through
this sort of environment um while uh and
you're not able to go through the walls.
In this case, the model might be quite
easy to learn. You'll learn that like if
your action is to go right, then you'll
go right unless there's a wall there. If
you're going to go up and so forth,
that's really easy. Uh but the policy is
really complicated. Uh because the
policy is saying that, okay, if you're
here, uh maybe you need to like go in
various different directions. And so
this is a case where the policy is a lot
more complicated than the model. And
learning a model could be a good choice.
Um, as another example, uh, say that you
have, um, you're trying to like pour
some water from one cup into like a bowl
or something like that. Uh, the policy
might be potentially fairly simple. Like
maybe you're already even like holding
uh the cup uh in your hand, then the
policy might be as simple as just like
rotating your wrist. Uh but the model in
this sort of case might involve like the
fluid dynamics of how the water will
pour and um what will happen for example
if it hits the edge of the bowl or the
center of the bowl or something like
that. And this is a scenario where the
model is a lot more complicated than the
policy. Uh and it's possible that it
would be um yeah in the scenario it
might be a lot easier to just learn the
policy without learning the model. So it
really depends on the domain. Yeah.
Yeah. So the question is how successful
has modelbased RL been in robotics
scenarios? Uh the if you can if you're
dealing with like highdimensional image
observations, uh it's arguably been less
successful. If you have a more compact
state space like the positions of joints
and positions of objects, then it's been
a lot more successful. And uh in like
with uh legged robots for example, you
can use model based RL um pretty
successfully uh if you if you're if
you're mostly just trying to learn like
a blind walking policy. uh or if like we
saw the the dextrous like the hand
manipulation where you knew the position
of the two balls uh that it was also
like very successful for that and I
haven't um trying to do model free RL
for that problem um or even imitation
learning like uh would be very very
challenging uh and so it's been
extremely successful there in scenarios
where you need have image observations
uh it gets a lot harder it doesn't mean
that um like it video generative models
are getting a lot better and so uh I can
see a future where uh these um this sort
of approach might also be um quite
successful in the future u but right now
it's not uh hasn't been super
successful.
The last thing that I'll mention on
modelbased RL is that so far we've been
modeling this predictive model of the
future and there's actually a lot of
other objects that you could learn. So
you could learn uh what's called an
inverse model. you could learn like four
two states like what was the action that
led to like if I were to if I'm
currently in state ST what is the action
that would lead to state ST plus one
um you could learn a multi-step inverse
model which is that uh what is the if
I'm going to end up at state ST plus N
what action would lead me there or what
are the sequence of actions that would
lead me there um this is actually looks
both of these in some ways look closer
to a policy except you're uh passing as
input some future state rather than um
just the current state. Uh these are
also things that can be learned without
data with rewards. Uh you're kind of
just learning about the environment and
not about the particular task at hand.
Uh you can predict futures without
actions and that kind of can think about
what are the affordances in my
environment. What are the things that um
that could be possible to happen in the
future irrespective of the actions that
I take.
You could uh try to interpolate between
two states. Uh you could learn a trans a
generative model of transitions of st
plus one. There's kind of some cool
properties uh with that sort of model.
Um and
these kind of models can be pretty
useful too. Uh they have various
purposes. Um there's lots of research on
using different kinds of models like
these. Uh and so it's just something to
to think about in terms of like in some
domains you could imagine or or with
some sort some data sources you could
imagine scenarios where these might be
useful. Yeah. So the question is um if
you use data that doesn't have rewards
as part of your model training is there
going to be a mismatch between the
accuracy of predicting next states and
predicting rewards? Uh the um there
certainly could be like a mismatch like
that. the
generally rewards are a bit easier to
learn how to predict than future states.
Uh and so the
um even if you have a lot more data for
learning the model, you could actually
end up in a scenario where the model is
less accurate than the the estimated
reward. Uh but you yeah, you can
definitely end up with scenarios where
the reward is is less accurate and uh
where you need to specifically gather
data for that. Um yeah,
cool. Okay. Um so that's it for model
based RL. Uh now we're going to talk a
bit about multitask learning um and what
that looks like uh and also different
techniques that we can do beyond like a
fairly naive and simple technique.
So um what is multitask reinforcement
learning? Uh the key idea is that we
want to be able to generate uh we want
to be able to learn a generalist policy
that isn't just aiming to do one thing
like being able to pour water for
example, but that can do many different
things.
The um examples of this uh we might want
kind of a generalist language model
assistant that can book travel for us,
that can do online grocery shopping. We
might want a legged robot that can walk,
that can run, that can dance, that can
crouch. Uh maybe a mobile robot that can
hang up a towel, unload a dishwasher,
wipe a spill. We want a music recommener
system that can personalize
recommendations for one person. Uh and
also be able to personalize
recommendations to a different person.
Uh or we might want something that can
play lots of different games, uh like
being able to play Pokemon and pinball
and and Flappy Bird and so forth.
And there are scenarios where if you
think about each of these tasks as their
own reinforcement learning problem, they
might have different reward functions
from the other tasks. They might in some
cases have different dynamics like the
dynamics of different games uh or the
dynamics of different people. Uh they
might have different action spaces even.
Uh and so when you're trying to train
policies across these different tasks,
there's some considerations that come up
uh when you try to uh yeah, when you try
to do that.
Um now the key idea that we'll see uh is
that you can in many cases just go about
normal reinforcement learning but
condition on the task that you're trying
to learn. Uh so you're then going to be
learning um a policy that is not just
conditioned on the state but it's also
condition it's conditioned on the state
and also the task that you want it to be
performing for that state.
Now uh why do we care about multitask
reinforcement learning? So um if we kind
of go back to a lot of the topics that
we've talked about in the course so far
like imitation learning on policy and
off policy RL offline RL model based RL
reward functions um a big topic that's
recurred uh in many of these lectures is
talking about data efficiency like how
how much data do we need to be able to
calculate a gradient that is accurate
and if our ultimate goal is to train
something that can do multiple tasks at
once, then we could actually amortize
the complexity of learning any one task
uh by actually training that policy
across tasks and across scenarios.
Uh so it could actually be a boost for
um data efficiency in the sense that the
task the data efficiency for training
any one task will be lower uh when
you're actually trying to train
everything together. Uh and that's
because tasks are going to have some
sort of typically will have some sort of
shared structure. Uh like if you're
trying to uh be a language model
assistant, uh there is going to be
shared structure with regard to grammar
or maybe with regard to different
websites. Um and if you learn how to
interact with one website, uh that can
teach you something about how to
interact with other websites. uh or or
like in robots, if your goal is to be
able to like walk forward and walk
backward, then this shared notion of
staying balanced will be shared across
tasks among other things. Uh or if
you're trying to develop a re recommener
system that's personalized to different
users, then some users will share a lot
of similarities where if you try to
learn to be a great recommener for one
person, then you should also there other
people that you could also probably be a
great recommener for.
Um and then there's also like a slightly
deeper motivation as well uh which is
that the uh when we actually try to
chain train ch train these generalist
systems rather than systems that do one
task uh we often find that generalist
systems end up being more reliable and
more performant than if we were to just
train on one task. Uh and so I think
that this is like kind of a pretty cool
finding that has kind of empirically
been true in recent years in AI. Uh and
so it's extra motivation for not just
training kind of something for one
particular uh task or problem or user.
Let's maybe get into what this actually
entails. And we actually need to think
about like what like how do we think
about what a task is? Uh it's actually
not in some ways not very well defined
like what makes something a different
task versus not a different task. Uh but
one way to think about it is having
different tasks just be different RL
problems, different markov decision
processes.
And so each task will have a state
space, an action space, uh an initial
state distribution, a transition model,
and a reward function.
Um, and I'm indexing these with index I
to denote that this is like the state
space for task I, this is the action
space for task I, uh, the dynamics and
and reward for task I and so forth.
Um now with this definition uh it's
worth mentioning that when we think of
the notion of a task uh we there's kind
of some English like there's a meaning
under the English word of task uh and
this notion of a task being an MTP is
actually potentially quite different
from that semantic notion of a task
where you could actually have different
tasks that have potentially the same
reward function and only have different
dynamics.
Uh, for example, the um
if you're trying to walk forward on
grass versus trying to walk forward on
flat terrain, then uh that potentially
could be considered two different tasks
under this framework, even though
they're both kind of the task of walking
forward. Okay. Um, so a few examples of
like kind of multitask problems that we
might think about. uh one is this kind
of personalized recommendation problem
that I mentioned uh in this case you
would different tasks would be different
users or different people and different
people might have different reward
functions like someone might if it's
music recommendations someone might
really love uh rock music another one
really personally might love hip-hop
music uh and also which tasks they um
kind of the dynamics with regard to uh
how um how often they even listen to
music and so forth might also change
across users.
Uh reinforcement learning has often
actually this is an application we
haven't really talked about but it's
often used uh in character animation in
order to actually create uh animations
of uh different kinds of characters like
uh like people or um or other like
animated characters that appear in
movies.
And you might want to learn a like allow
and be able to animate a character to do
lots of different maneuvers. Uh so you
might want to be able to have your
character be able to do a backflip or to
be able to run or be able to do a
cartwheel. Uh and each of these would be
different tasks.
Uh does anyone have thoughts for these
tasks? What is the thing that would vary
across tasks versus be fixed across
tasks? Yeah. So in this scenario, the
reward will vary uh because in one case
you want it to run, in another case you
want it to do a cartwheel uh and the
dynamics or the physics of the simulator
uh will stay the same. Um
cool. Uh there's also been like works
that's trying to do character animation
involving like uh different like
garments. So like a character that could
put on a shirt versus like a long sleeve
shirt versus a dress. Uh does anyone
have thoughts on what would vary across
these tasks? Yeah. So the policy might
vary. The policy will also vary actually
in all of these cases uh for different
tasks. Yeah. So the the kind of the
physics of how a long sleeve shirt
versus a short sleeve shirt will behave.
It will vary across tasks. Um I think I
also put the initial state distribution
might also vary. Um whereas like in the
first example that maybe the initial
state is always like to stay like start
standing up for example. Um whereas here
you have different like garments in the
initial state. Um and then the last
example I put is uh maybe different
tasks are controlling different robot
arms. Uh and maybe one robot arm looks
like this with like uh like maybe four
degrees of freedom. This one is six
degrees of freedom. This one is seven
degrees of freedom. Um, does anyone have
thoughts on what would vary across
tasks? If different tasks, if one task
is like to control the first robot to
grasp an object, the second task is to
control the second robot to grasp an
object and so forth. Yeah. So the
actions themselves uh so you'll have
like different dimensions of actions.
Yeah. So the dynamics will also be
different because when you move one
joint that will affect the other joints
differently.
Yeah. So the states would also vary as
well. So um the like how you represent
the arm like it'll like that will be a
different dimension. Uh what the actions
even are will also be uh different
dimensional and then the dynamics will
also vary quite a bit as well because
how how your actions affect the robot
arm are going to change.
Cool. Um so those are the examples of
like different problems where we might
want to be uh kind of training uh
different tasks. Um the last thing is
that uh that we're kind of missing here
is we need to figure out how to identify
one task from another task. Uh so that
we can tell uh our policy what task it
should be doing uh at a given point.
Uh and one way to do this is to just
assign an index. You can say like this
robot is task zero, this robot is task
one, this robot is task two and so
forth. Uh this is like if you don't have
any other kind of better way to identify
a task, this is kind of what you resort
to.
Uh you could also have a language
description of the task. Uh you could
have a video illustration of what the
task is. Uh there's actually a number of
ways to be creative with how you
describe the task to the policy. Um and
we'll refer to each of these as um
different task identifiers. So uh the
task identifier for the task of um well
actually we'll we'll see some examples
uh on the next slide.
Now once you have the task identifier um
an alternative view on the multitask RL
problem is simply just having the task
identifier be part of the state where
we're writing sbar as the original
state. Uh and what this means is that
before we had a kind of a collection of
MVPs uh that's kind of what's written at
the top and we can actually construct
uh a
we can kind of construct a single MDP
that actually covers all of the tasks.
So the um
we have for example uh the like pi of
the initial state pi of s prime given sa
and r i of a and this is like the
dynamics and the reward for each task.
Uh, and
we can kind of think of it as like our
goal is to solve all of the MDPs for
each of the tasks. But we can also think
about it as just a single MDP where the
um the state is now defined as like
maybe this is like the
uh original state space of these tasks
and the state is now defined as like the
original state space uh and the task
identifier for that task. And then the
reward function for example in this
modified MDP that's just a single MDP
for all the tasks is then going to be uh
equal to let's say just to be explicit
um
the reward for uh for this state
and this action would then be equal to R
I of
Sbar
uh A. And similarly you can write
something out for the dynamics as well
where the MDP uh the kind of the
aggregated MDP for uh
a given task
s prime given sbar
zi
comma a is equal to the kind of dynamics
for that task.
This gets a little bit more complicated
if your tasks have different state
spaces and action spaces. Uh but there
and and so you'd have to if they have
for example different dimensionalities
then [clears throat] you need to think
about how you would represent this state
space in the MTP. Uh if they have the
same state space and action space um you
can basically construct this aggregated
mark decision process uh with this
equations here.
Now,
um, if we go back to kind of, uh,
kind of the what we think of as like the
single task reinforcement learning
setting that we've talked about so far,
we can then kind of think about
multitask RL uh, but where the task
identifier is part of the state. Um,
where the task identifier could be the
task like an index, a language
description. Um, it can also be some
desired goal state as well that you want
to reach. Um, this is often referred to
as goal conditioned RL. Um, but then
once you do this, you're basically
getting uh a a modified MVP that covers
each of these tasks.
Um, now in terms of the reward, like we
talked about on the board, uh, it's
basically going to be the same as
before. Uh in this special case of goal
conditioned reinforcement learning where
you're trying to reach a goal, uh then
often times you'll think about the
reward as some uh negative distance
between the state that you're currently
at and the goal state.
Um and distance functions could be
uklidian, it could be a sparse one, uh
and so forth. So we still get kind of a
standard marov decision process when we
aggregate when we kind of uh bring these
tasks together. And you might ask if
it's kind of if we can get this standard
Markov decision process that now has a
task identifier like a task string as
part of the state space then why not
apply kind of standard reinforcement
learning algorithms to them. Uh and the
answer is you can. uh and in many cases
this is a great way to approach like
scenarios where you want to learn
multiple tasks uh but the reason why I'm
bringing all this up is there in some
cases you can actually do better uh by
leveraging the uh kind of known
structure between different tasks uh and
goal condition RL is one of those cases
where you're trying to reach different
goals uh and uh in the kind of next few
slides we'll talk about um one
particular way that you can do a lot
better by um leveraging this fact that
you know that this MDP consists of these
different tasks that you're trying to
do. Yeah. Uklidian L2 that's just means
square. Yeah. Yeah. So the question is
uh if people are different people are
different tasks then is there a better
way better way to recommend or better
way to represent different people than
like a one hot um like when when when I
say one hot by the way I mean um kind of
a vector like this uh where like if
you're going to represent the number two
you use like a one hot vector um the so
yeah there are different like definitely
better ways than just this uh this is
actually fairly common uh in a lot of
reinforcement learning methods
But for example, um, one thing you could
do is you could try to get a language
description of the person or their
preferences. Uh, you could also,
um, this kind of gets into stuff that
we'll talk about next week, but you
could also, uh, use some examples of
things that they like and don't like as
part of the task descriptor as well. uh
and so you get something more like in
context learning uh in that case where
DI um actually might contain some data
about the task. Uh so yeah there are
some some better examples like that.
So in terms of this problem setup let's
actually like look at an example. Uh so
we get to start with multitask imitation
learning. And in the multitask imitation
learning setting uh we can think of it
as if we have different tasks I um
the if the number of tasks I is like a
relatively small number then you might
you can basically think of it as having
uh some set of demonstrations
uh that are demonstration trajectories
for each task uh where each of these
contains expert demonstrations um and
then you'll have Uh so these are
demos for
task I and this is for like uh I equals
like 1 2 n if you have n different
tasks.
And if we were to think about how to use
this data for imitation learning, uh
kind of thinking back to the very first
lecture or second lecture we were doing
imitation learning, we had this
objective of minimizing the log
probability of actions given states. And
if we just write this as minimizing some
the kind of supervised loss function uh
with respect to our policy parameters
then in when we want to move to the
multitask setting what we can do is we
can simply try to now minimize a single
policy set of policy parameters over the
loss function averaged over all of the
tasks.
So this is basically like multitask
invitation learning pretty simple
hopefully. Uh, one useful trick for this
sort of approach is that um, if you if
tasks are very different, like if one
task is telling you to go forwards, one
task is telling you to go backwards, uh,
maybe one task is telling you to lie
down, they're like they're telling the
policy to do very different things, then
if you sampled one mini batch that's
like mostly going forward and a
different mini batch of mostly laying
down, for example, then from one
gradient step to the next, you're
actually going to have a lot of variance
because the first mini batch is going to
tell you to do something that's pretty
different from the second mini batch.
Uh, and hopefully the policy should be
able to use the task identifier to
differentiate the two. Uh, but in some
cases it can be a little bit ch like
tricky for the network to do that. Uh,
and so one thing that's quite useful is
that when you sample a mini batch, you
can stratify the mini batch and ensure
that each mini batch of data has data
from each task. Uh and if you're trying
to optimize for kind of a uniform
distribution over your tasks, then your
mini batch would be like uh one over n
of the data would be the first task, one
over n of the mini batch would be the
second task and so forth. Uh and this
will give you uh gradients that are
lower variance. Uh and it can be quite
useful in practice uh to do something
like this. Another thing that I didn't
put on the slides that can also be
useful is making sure that your um that
your states and actions are on similar
scales across tasks. So kind of per task
normalization uh can also be quite
useful for the learning process.
Now we've talked about training this
multitask policy. Uh, and when we do
that, we're going to have we're now
going to have a policy that takes as
input some state and some task
descriptor and is then needs to output
some action. Uh, and you might have
scenarios where like this is like a like
a language string or a one hot vector
and this is an image and those are
that's inherently like a very multimodal
problem like you have different data
modalities. These are like very
different dimensions. Uh and so in
practice there's a question of how do
you design architectures that take as
input this kind of multimodal data.
Um, one example that I'll give that I
kind of like because it actually uh uses
multiple different modalities of task
descriptors um is uh this paper here
where uh the goal is like a multitask
imitation learning system is training a
robot uh to do some simple manipulation
tasks
and uh the way the architecture works
this paper's a little bit old so it's
not using a transformer uh but here's
the current state right here uh it
actually downsamples the image uh before
passing it into the
Uh and then it also uses actually two
different tasks descriptors. So it uses
a language string as one tasks
descriptor which is put bottle in the
ceramic bowl. Uh and it also trains the
model to be able to instead of using the
language be able to use a video of how
to do the task. Uh in this case the
video is a video of a person uh placing
the bottle in the bowl.
Uh and so you can um and design models
that in this case then uh for the
language it would use a language encoder
like uh uh like kind of things that are
typically used uh in language models uh
for example transformers. Uh and
actually I think the language encoder
here did actually use a transformer. Um
and then separately for the video it
would be using a different kind of
encoder because video data looks very
different and it uses a video encoder
for the second part. And then uh it kind
of puts it kind of multiplies these
embeddings into different layers of um
the network kind of the backbone of the
network that processes the state.
Um and then the loss function uh
corresponds to a behavior cloning loss.
Uh and it either samples the task
descriptor from the video encoder or
from the language encoder. And then the
whole model is trained with including
these encoders is trained using uh the
behavior cloning loss.
Um so this is like kind of one practical
example. Um, now we can also look at
some more modern architectures. And uh,
first off, if you have something like a
language model, the task descriptor,
it's very natural for it just to be a
language string. And you can think of
that basically just as the prompt. And
so in many ways, like one way to think
about multitask imitation learning is
basically all of the language model
imitation learning or supervised
fine-tuning is with different prompts.
You can sort of think of those as
different tasks. Um, and it's very easy
to just pass that into a transformer.
Uh, and in terms of modern policy
architectures, uh, for using task
strings in robotics, uh, it's often
common to also use a transformer, uh,
and find ways to, uh, use image
encoders, in this case, kind of
pre-trained image encoders, uh, project
those into the input space of a language
model. Um, also use the task descriptor
here, um, which is what should the robot
do to put the eggplant in the bowl, pass
those in as tokens to a language model,
um, and then output the actions and
train the whole model including the
image encoder and the text encoder and
pen.
Um, so here you can yeah view the task
encoder, the task identifier uh, ZI as
basically the prompt for the model. Uh
the question is how does this compare to
traditional reinforcement learning
um in terms of task performance and
success rate? So the um
so like I guess there's a couple things
that are different here. We'll talk
about multitask RL um in a bit like
right after this. Uh and then so the
like you can do both the sort of like
prompt conditioning task identifier
conditioning both with imitation
learning and with reinforcement
learning. uh and generally the
considerations about imitation learning
versus RL is very similar to what we've
discussed so far where with imitation
learning um you're not able to use a
reward function to improve over the
expert data uh but it's very simple uh
and it's very easy to scale simple
things to large data sets uh whereas RL
has a lot of potential in and and can
help a lot when you have some reward
information and you want to optimize
those uh rewards and you can actually do
a lot better than um than some pre uh
some provided data set and then just
some examples of like what kind of
multitask imitation learning policies
might look like. Uh the examples from
those kind of two prior architectures
like um the robots are doing very simple
things and so I wanted to pick something
that's a bit more recent. Uh so here the
task identifier is in the top left. Uh
in this video there'll just be two
tasks. One is to flatten the towel and
one is to hang the towel. And so um for
the first part the task is to flatten
the towel. And then here we're actually
stringing together multiple tasks. Um so
at the point where the robot um is at a
point where it's like better, it's like
the towel is in a more flattened state,
the human actually switches the task and
then tells the robot, now I want you to
hang the towel. Um and that this again
is passed into a transformer um for the
robot to do that task. So this is a case
where there's two tasks. Um you can also
do actually a lot more tasks
potentially. So, here's an example where
there's I think more than 10 tasks that
10 different language strings that the
robot follows um to like put the plate
in the drawer, uh close the microwave,
drive the base backward, rotate the base
left. And one of the things that's
interesting to note here is that tasks
can also have different levels of
abstraction. So, you might have a level
of abstraction of just like drive
forward or like move your right gripper
lower um or you might have something
that's much higher like um throw the
napkin away uh or something like that.
The question is if you had mult like one
policy for each task, would that run
similar to this um or different? Yeah.
So in this case it's one policy kind of
with the prompt as input. You could also
have a different policy one for each
task. uh if you have if you don't do any
like what I would call weight sharing
like if you have basically completely
different set of parameters for every
single task then um you can't really
make use of uh like the weights are only
trained on data from that one task and
you're going to have a smaller data set
and so usually um in many scenarios that
performs worse than training a single
policy. Uh, another consideration is
that it ends up using a lot more memory
to store all those weights and you might
actually need to reload the model um
into memory and so it can be take longer
to switch between different tasks. Um,
but sometimes there are also
optimization challenges with trying to
fit multiple tasks into one model. Um,
and so sometimes there are some
circumstances where training different
policies for different tasks can be
useful. Yeah. So the question is are
these systems um hierarchical like some
of these tasks are fairly high level? Um
so the next part of this slide is what
about like even more highle tasks like
what if you wanted to tell the robot
clean the kitchen. Um for this
particular um for the videos that I've
shown here this is just like one single
policy that's doing it. Um but hierarchy
is like very useful for like higher
level tasks. And if you just told this
robot to clean the kitchen it wouldn't
be able to do what it did in this video.
uh and so we'll have a lecture on
hierarchy in like I think two-ish weeks
uh and we'll talk about exactly that um
and scenarios where we could try to do
uh even higher level tasks uh but yeah
even with a single policy a single flat
policy without hierarchy it is able to
do um kind of reasonable actions for
tasks that are somewhat high level. Oh
what does long horizon task mean? uh by
that I mean a task that takes a long
time basically uh where you have to like
takes many time steps you have to take a
lot of different actions in order to do
that uh and there's generally a number
of challenges that can come up with long
horizon tasks such as uh like the you
have to be thinking about what you
should be doing um in order to complete
that and there's lots of things you
could do to complete that. And so they
might be multimodality in reinforcement
learning settings. You might also have
sparse rewards and you might not get
reward feedback for a very long time.
Yeah. So the question is um a lot of
these tasks are pretty similar. What if
you wanted a task that's more vision
based? I think you said um the Yeah. So
in this actually this particular model
was actually also trained to do certain
vision tasks like asking questions about
the image uh and um and like capturing
an image that sort of stuff. Uh, and it
could actually like it's actually not
too if you have a big enough model, it's
not too hard to do that. Um, but
generally you do need larger models to
be able to do more things.
Cool. Um, so we talked a bit about
multitask imitation learning. Now what
about multitask RL? Uh, basically the
kind of the story is pretty similar. uh
we can feed as input a task descriptor
into the policy feed as input a task
descriptor into a Q function or a value
function like whatever we're learning we
can pass in that sort of that prompt uh
or some other descriptor of the task
into the models.
Um
if you um if you have a discrete number
of tasks then it can be useful to have a
different replay buffer for each task
especially if you want to try to balance
the sampling of each batch.
uh and now there's this question of um
sharing data. So like in then this is
comes up specifically in reinforcement
learning not in imitation learning. So
uh in particular if we collected some
sort of exploratory data for a task um
when like maybe our policy was told to
like uh pick up the sponge or something
like that. Uh we our policy did
something it might not have picked up
the sponge because it may have made a
mistake. uh that sort of experience
might be useful for other task
descriptors as well. And if we have like
a per task replay buffer like one for
each task, then we're not actually going
to be updating the policy for other
tasks using that data. And we could
actually think about scenarios where um
we might actually be able to reuse data
from one task to actually more
explicitly help the the um the the model
or the policy learn something about
another task.
And if we were to do this, we actually
have to re label the data. So um that
specifically like if the tasks have
different reward functions but maybe the
same dynamics then you'd have to
actually change the reward label in the
data set for to be the the reward label
for the other task.
Let's walk through an example. So say
that you are trying to learn to play
hockey
and
you uh there's like maybe um some
teammates in blue. there is a goalkeeper
from the other team in orange. Uh and
maybe one task is like is passing.
Another task is shooting a goal.
And um maybe you were trying to shoot a
goal uh but you messed up and you
accidentally uh actually making a like a
pretty good pass uh to your uh your
teammate.
then that data that you just collected,
even though you were intending to shoot
a goal, that data actually is probably
pretty useful for learning how to be
better at passing.
And so what you could do is you could
store that experience as normal under
the original task identifier, but you
could also reabel the experience with uh
task the um with the task one ID uh
specifically the passing ID. There's a
typo there. And then store that in a
repo buffer for that task.
And so specifically
what this algorithm would look like is
um maybe you have uh
you pick one of your tasks
uh and then we pick a corresponding task
identifier. Then we're going to
collect data
and we'll be collecting data from
our policy
that's going to be then conditioned on
that task identifier.
Then um and maybe let's refer to this
data as like it'll have ST a t
ST + one
RT and then it will also
uh have the task identifier. We'll maybe
put this into a replay buffer for uh
task I. So, we'll store this um in the
replay buffer
and then we could actually then
potentially use this for another task as
well. So, that's what I'm calling
relabeling.
And we could consider this data. So, ST
A T S + one, but we could actually
consider it for a different task, maybe
task J. And so the reward for task J
would be R of J for ST A and the task
identifier for task J. And we could take
this data that's been relabeled and add
this to either our shared replay buffer
or our replay buffer for task J.
And so then we're actually using
experience for one task uh to um learn
another task.
Uh and then
we might uh we might do this for
multiple tasks. Uh eventually we will
update our policy pi theta uh and kind
of collect some more data. Yeah. So the
question is how do we decide if it's
worth reabeling? And in particular we're
doing this for task j uh like which task
j should we pick? Should we do it for
all js? Should we u only do it for some
js? Should we only do this some of the
time? Um, this ends up being somewhat
kind of of a heristic process because
it's a little bit hard to tell generally
if data will be useful for learning one
task or not. Um, because learning is
somewhat like of a amorphous process. I
guess uh the one heristic is that if RJ
was high uh then it might be good for
learning that task because it uh you
actually might have accidentally done
something good for a different task. Uh
so that's one one heristic. Uh another
heristic something is sometimes is just
to also sample randomly um and use it
for for all tasks at random and
uniformly.
How does this work for continuous state?
Uh there's nothing here that assumes
discrete states. How do you reach? So
this is actually um what I've written
here is like a reabeling algorithm for
any sort of multitask. Um there's also
we'll talk about what this looks like
for a goal condition settings uh in a
minute if that's what you're wondering
about. Yeah. So this is a great point.
Um there's only a few scenar like there
only you can't do this universally. Uh
and so
this is this is something that's called
hindsight reabeling because you kind of
look at what what you did. Um if you did
something good then in hindsight you can
kind of then relabel that to be a
different task.
So in terms of this algorithm on the
board or on the slides, uh we collect
some data using some policy. We store
that data in a replay buffer. Um we're
going to perform hindsight reabeling. Uh
and what this looks like is this. We
originally collected it for task I.
We're going to reabel it um with the
reward for task J.
And then we'll store that reabelled data
in a replay buffer. Uh the slides have
this for like a a single combined replay
buffer. You could also do this with
different replay buffers for each task.
Uh then you'll update your policy with
the replay buffer and repeat this
process.
Um in terms of which task to choose, you
can choose this randomly. Tasks that get
high rewards. Um you the note here is
also you can actually do it for
trajectories that get high rewards, not
just transitions that get high rewards.
Uh because if there's a high reward
somewhere in the trajectory, then other
parts of the trajectory might have done
something good as well.
Um yeah and then there's a question of
when can we apply reabeling
uh and in particular there's actually
restrictions on both the like the m the
set of MDPs or like the MDPs of the
different tasks and also on uh the
algorithm that you're using for
reinforcement learning. Um, so does
anyone have thoughts on like what has to
be shared or not shared uh for this
algorithm to make sense? Yeah. So shared
state action space. Uh so that's you're
going to want um a shared
uh state and action space.
Uh anything else do you want
that's shared and not shared? Yeah.
Yeah. So if you only have one replay
buffer, then you want the dimensions of
your state and actions to match. Um the
and generally for the state space and
action space to be the same. Yeah. So
you probably want the initial state
distribution to be similar. Um so you
want like P of S1
uh for to be like similar
uh for different um
for different tasks. Uh because if it's
like drastically different then they're
probably like sharing data won't be as
useful. Um so if if one of them has
denser words and one of those has sparse
words that might be a problem. Um
that is true. Uh although that might be
a problem generally uh in multitask RL
um well and but actually in this case
like I don't think it's going to be
especially an issue in this case because
you are going to be using the reward
function for the task but yeah generally
for multitask that makes things
challenging. Yeah so it's helpful for
the rewards to be the same scale. What
about the dynamics?
Should they be the same or different
across tasks? Same. Yeah. So, you want
the dynamics to be the same. And this
actually really important because you're
not relabeling the dynamics here. Uh and
because you're not relabeling the
dynamics, if they're different across
tasks, then uh you're going to be you
have yeah, it's going to be a problem.
Uh and so this is only applicable
because you're because you're teaching
the model and sharing data with the
dynamics from the other task. It's
really important for the dynamics to be
the same.
Um so the dynamics should be the same.
Uh and then this is also most useful if
the reward functions are different. Um
otherwise uh the data like is already in
the buffer uh with the original reward
function. Uh my last question is uh do
you need like do you need this to be an
off policy RL algorithm or um is it okay
if this is on policy?
Any thoughts on that? We'd like to have
covers off policy is generally good.
Yeah. Yeah. So when we um
the action here um this was the action
that was taken by the policy when
conditioned on ZI and when conditioned
on Zj the policy might have done
something different. And so this data
that we're relabeling is going to be off
policy data. Uh and so that means that
we should when we're updating Pytha, we
really need to be using an off policy
algorithm uh because this data um is not
following the policy conditioned on Zj.
Yeah, exactly. So if you're going to be
using importance weights, you need to
store which policy collected the data uh
in the first place. Uh well,
actually, sorry, let me think about
that. Um
you're actually create like
uh this data is actually like changed
from the original data and so actually
you you'll want to use um for the like
the importance you'll actually want to
use Zj not ZI um as the old policy uh
because you're actually kind of creating
like synthetic data that like is as if
you were um using Zj. So yeah, sorry I
misspoke. You you don't and so you don't
need to store which policy it came from.
Okay, so you need the reward function.
Oh, the other thing is you need the
reward function form here. You need to
actually compute the rewards for the new
task. That's also important as well. Um,
or you need to have learned the reward
function. So, you need the reward
function. The dynamics has to be
consistent and you have to be using an
off policy algorithm. Um, and then
lastly is the goal condition version.
This is basically the same as before,
but our reward function is now this
negative distance between states. And
for continuous states, uh, this could be
like mean squared error, could be a
distance in embedding space. Uh or it
could be um a zero one loss within some
epsilon ball of the goal state.